Register of the Ivan V. Emel'ianov Papers, 1908-1960
Hoover Institution Archives
- Ivan V. Emel'Ianov, 1915-1951
  - Subject file, 1920-1941
    - Agriculture, Cooperative--"Selosoyus" and "Sel'skosoiuz." Includes materials relating to the above organizations and Moskovsky Narodny Bank, collected or produced in the course of Emel'ianov's duties as representative of these organizations abroad, 1920-1922
      - Correspondence (Folder 2)
      - Letterbooks. Also include unrelated correspondence and writings, in part materials dealing with the establishment of agricultural cooperative courses in Prague, and the works "Puti russkoi zemlediel'cheskoi kooperatsii" and "K voprosu ob organizatsii miestnago samoupravleniia na Donu," n.d. Holograph, 1921 (Folder 3)
      - Minutes of meetings (Folder 4)
    - Dobrynia-Koniukhov, P. Collection of his writings and scientific sketches (Folder 5)
    - Dostoevsky, Fedor. Correspondence and other materials relating to commemoration of anniversary of his birth, Correspondents include Serge Koussevitzky, Pitirim Sorokin, Serge Ughet, G. V. Vernadsky, 1931. (Folder 6)
    - Khoziain (periodical) (Folder 7)
    - Ob"edinennye russkie natsional'nye organizatsii. Minutes of meetings, correspondence and printed matter (Folder 8)
    - Obshchestvo dlia vzaimnogo strakhovaniia loshadei. Charter, 1920 March 30 (Folder 9)
    - Obshchestvo druzei russkoi kul'tury. Minutes of meetings, 1930 (Folder 10)
    - Pushkin, Aleksandr. Correspondence and other materials relating to celebrations in his honor, 1935-1941 (Folder 11)
    - Russians--Foreign countries--Organizations. Appeals, bulletins and other matter issued by or relating to various émigré organizations (Folder 12)
    - Russkii institut sel'sko-khoziaistvennoi kooperatsii. Includes minutes of meeting relating to its establishment, See also Subject File/Agriculture, Cooperative/Letterbooks, 1921 June 30. (Folder 13)
    - Russkoe sel'sko-khoziaistvennoe obshchestvo. Includes clippings and photograph of members, 1938 (Folder 14)
    - Soiuz "Russkii zemledielets" (Folder 15)
    - Zavalishin, Boris. Correspondence and printed matter (Folder 16)
    - Miscellany (Folder 17)
  - Printed matter, 1896-1944
    - General and unidentified (Folder 18)
    - Belgium. Ministère de l'Agriculture et des Travaux Publics, Exposé statistique de la situation des associations d'intérêt agricole pendant l'année 1910 (Brussels, 1912); Bilimovich, A. D., K voprosu ob ekonomicheskoi programmie natsional'noi Rossii (Belgrade, 1936); Biulleten' Ekonomicheskogo kabineta prof. S. N. Prokopovicha, #84 (Dec. 1930); Commission pour la Reconstitution de l'Industrie Minière et Métallurgique de la Russie Méridionale, Bulletin, #190-208 (incomplete), (1930-1932) (Folder 19)
    - Dvorzhak, L. F., Kooperatsiia v Chekhoslovakii (Prague, 1921); Galtsoff, P. S., Pearl and Hermes Reef, Hawaii, Hydrographical and Biological Observations (Honolulu, 1933); Gsovski, Vladimir, "The Soviet Concept of Law," Fordham Law Review, January 1938; International Institute of Agriculture, An Outline of the European Co-Operative Credit Systems, Second Edition (Rome, 1913) (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Jahrbuch des Reichsverbands der deutschen landwirtschaftlichen Genossenschaften, 1926 (Berlin, 1926); Khimshiev, N. V., Prince, O politicheskoi preemstvennosti (Sofia, 1931); Kievskoe tovarishchestvo zapadnykh zemstv, Zemskie banki (Kiev, 1918); Lozovyi, Aleksandr, Sel'sko-khoziaistvennaia kooperatsiia (Moscow, 1923) (missing cover and pp., 1-16) (Folder 2)
    - Malitskii, N., Kooperatsiia sredi zemlediel'tsev v Bolgarii (Prague, 1922); Marakuev, S. V., Ocherednyia zadachi russkoi kooperatsii (Prague, 1921); Miakotin, V. A., Pereiaslavskii dogovor 1654-go goda (Prague, 1930); Obshcherusskoe ob"edinenie v Amerikie, Plan Organizatsii Prosvietitel'nogo Diela Pri Obshcherusskom Ob"edinenii v Amerikie (Wilkes-Barre, PA, 1931); Prokopovich, P. I., Kooperatsiia v sel'skom khoziaistvie (Prague, 1926); Prokopovich, S. N., Krest"ianskoe khoziaistvo (Berlin, 1924) (Folder 3)
    - Protokol o Rádném Ríském sjedu Republikanské strany Zemedelského a Malorolnického Lidu ve Dnech 7. A 8. Kvetna 1929 (Prague, 1929); Russia: Semi-Monthly Magazine (v. 1, #1, 1 October 1944); Shakhmatov, M. V., Opravdanie bogatstva (Paris, 1927); Shvegla, Antonin, Cheloviek i zemlia (Prague 1924); Sorokin, P. A., Ideologiia agrarizma (Prague, 1924); Trudy pervago s"ezda russkikh dieiatelei sel'skago khoziaistva, Vyp. I (Prague, 1925) (Folder 4)
    - Union Centrale des Syndicats des Agriculteurs de France. Various leaflets and publications, c. 1920-1921 (Folder 5)
    - Uzefovich, Alexis, "Graphical Determination of the Distance Between Two Given Points on or Near the Surface of the Earth," School Science and Mathematics, v. XXVIII, #9 (Dec. 1928); The Western Frontier of Russia (New York, 1944); Zaitsev, K., "The Agrarian Question in Russia," Journal of Economic and Business History, v. III, #4 (August 1931); Zaitsev, K., "Stroi upravleniia Chekhoslovatskoi respubliki" (excerpt from unidentified periodical); Zeitschrift für Nationalökonomie (Band II, Heft 3, 15 Jan. 1931 - issue devoted to examination of Aleksandr Bilimovich's financial theories); Zvorykin, Nikolai, Propriétaires et paysans russes (Paris, 1896) (Folder 6)
- Nataliia V. Emel'Ianova, 1908-1960
  - Biographical file, 1908-1960
    - Clippings from newspapers about N. V. Emel'ianova, 1934 and undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Curriculum vitae (Folder 2)
    - Educational records, 1908-1925. Includes documents from Khar'kov Women's Gimnaziia and Charles University (Folder 3)
    - Employment records. Includes application forms and correspondence (Folder 4)
    - Letters of recommendation (Folder 5)
    - Subject file - New York Academy of Sciences. Correspondence and other matter relating to Emel'ianova's membership (Folder 6)
    - Miscellany (Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, See also IVAN V. EMEL'IANOV for correspondence addressed to both Ivan and Nataliia, 1920-1952.
    - General, 1933-1952 (Folder 8)
    - Unidentified, 1920-1938 and undated (Folder 9)
    - Alekseeva, E., 1933 (Folder 10)
    - Bogert, Marston T., 1928-1941 (Folder 11)
    - Brunst, Viktor Emil'evich, 1928 (Folder 12)
    - Georgievskaia, V., 1927 (Folder 13)
    - Gerasimenko, P., 1928-1929 (Folder 14)
    - Heyrovský, J., 1926-1933 (Folder 15)
    - Ianata (Janata), S., 1935 (Folder 16)
    - Kalishevskii, A., Includes undated latter from V. Kalishevskaia, 1936. (Folder 17)
    - Kay, Lidiia, 1933-1936 (Folder 18)
    - Kolesov, F., 1934 and undated (Folder 19)
    - Komitet po sooruzheniiu pamiatnika russkim voinam, pavshim na frantsuzskom frontie, Includes printed matter and photographs of the monument to fallen Russian soldiers on the Western Front of the First World War, 1936. (Folder 20)
    - Kondakov, I. L., 1928-1929 (Folder 21)
    - Kukulevskaia, V., 1933-1938 and undated (Folder 22)
    - Mel'nikov, N. ( Rossiia), 1934 (Folder 23)
    - Morgan, Rose, n.d. (Folder 24)
    - Moskova, Olga, 1934 (Folder 25)
    - Nevalonny (Nevalonaja), Anna, Includes photograph of her, 1933-1934. (Folder 26)
    - Ototskii, P., 1930-1937 (Folder 27)
    - Romanov, Maksim, 1934 (Folder 28)
    - Rot, Nadezhda, 1927-1934 (Folder 29)
    - Russkaia akademicheskaia gruppa v Chekhoslovakii, 1932 (Folder 30)
    - Solodovnikov, K., 1921 (Folder 31)
    - Spolek Pomoci Ruským Detem v CSR, 1935 (Folder 32)
    - Sproge, Wilhelm, 1949 (Folder 33)
    - Vilkov, A., 1930-1936 (Folder 34)
  - Writings, 1925-1933 and undated
    - General
      - Correspondence with Biological Abstracts regarding Emel'ianova's submissions, 1936-1937 (Box 13, Folder 1)
      - Scientific notes (Folder 2)
    - "Analysa kvalitativní," Holograph. Fragmentary Russian text, n.d. (Folder 3)
    - "Paskha," Typescript. Includes handwritten English translation (Folder 4)
    - Researches with the Dropping Mercury Cathode: Nickel and Cobalt, Printed copy, 1925. (Folder 5)
    - "The Phenomenon of Maxima Occurring on Polarization Curves of Nickel-Salt Solutions," Bulletin international de l'Académie des Sciences de Bohême, 1927. Printed copy. Includes Czech edition: "Studium maxim na polarisacních krivkách rotoku nikelnatých solí," Rozpravy II. Trídy Ceské Akademie, Printed copy (Folder 6)
    - Maxima on Current-Voltage Curves, Part I, Printed copy, 1928 May. (Folder 7)
    - "A New Method for Staining Bacterial Capsules," Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, Printed copy, 1932. (Folder 8)
    - "Presence of Capsules on 'Non-Capsulated' Microorganisms," Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, Printed copy, 1932. (Folder 9)
    - "Bacterial Structure with Particular Reference to the Capsule," Proceedings of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1932. Printed copy. Includes notice of presentation of above paper at a meeting of the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, 1932 May 18 (Folder 10)
    - Translation of an appeal by Countess A. L. Tolstoy, Holograph and typescript, 1933 January 31. (Folder 11)
    - "A Study of the Bacterial Capsule by New Methods," (with John W. Churchman), The Journal of Experimental Medicine, Printed copy. Includes typewritten draft and correspondence with co-author John W. Churchman, 1932, 1933 March 1. (Folder 12)
    - Miscellany. Jottings, drafts, and fragments of translations (I. A. Bunin's "Boginia" and a story by Dostoevsky) (Folder 13)
  - Printed matter. Includes miscellaneous clippings as well as scientific articles by Emel'ianova's associates, John W. Churchman, P. Herasymenko (Gerasimenko), J. Heyrovský, I. Kondakov and others (Folder 14)
- Photographs, c. 1921-1940s
  - Albums
    - General
      - Groups and individuals associated primarily with Prague period (Box 14, Folder 1)
      - Unidentified individuals, groups and landscapes (Folder 2)
    - "Horni Cernoice, ", 1924 (Folder 3)
  - Ivan V. Emel'ianov, including his funeral (Folder 4)
  - Nataliia V. Emel'ianova (Folder 5)
  - Nataliia V. Emel'ianova and associates in her research laboratory (Prague) (Folder 6)
  - The Emel'ianovs together and with unidentified individuals (Folder 7)
  - Groups associated with the Russkii institut sel'sko-khoziaistvennoi kooperatsii, Prague (Folder 8)
  - Shindler, Camille Gavrilovich and Eliaveta Afanes'evna, including the latter's funeral, 1927 (Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified individuals, include Vasilii Benzin, Ivan Pavlov, and others (Folder 10)
  - Vacation photos, landscapes, houses, solar eclipse and other (Folder 11)
  - Negatives and glass plates (Folder 12)